<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  DIRECTIVE (EU) 2015/849 — 4th Anti-Money Laundering Directive (AMLD4)
  Machine-readable taxonomy of obligations applicable to OBLIGED ENTITIES.
  
  Scope: Covers only provisions that impose direct duties on obliged entities
         (credit institutions, financial institutions, and the professional
         categories listed in Article 2(1)(3)).
  Purpose: RAG / AI-assisted compliance reference.
  Simplified: Legislative recitals and Member State transposition instructions
              are removed; only the core obligation content is retained.
-->

<AMLD4_ObligedEntity_Obligations
  directive="Directive (EU) 2015/849"
  date="2015-05-20"
  source="OJ L 141, 5.6.2015, p. 73"
  transposition_deadline="2017-06-26">

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER I — RISK ASSESSMENT (Articles 6–8)
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="I-RiskAssessment" title="Risk Assessment">

    <Article id="8" title="Obliged Entity-Level Risk Assessment"
             obligation_type="Risk Management">
      (1) Obliged entities must identify and assess their money laundering
          and terrorist financing (ML/TF) risks, taking into account risk
          factors relating (among others) to: customers, countries or geographic areas,
          products, services, transactions, and delivery channels. The
          assessment must be proportionate to the nature and size of the
          entity.
      (2) Risk assessments must be documented, kept up to date, and made
          available to competent authorities or self-regulatory bodies on
          request.
      (3) Obliged entities must have in place policies, controls, and
          procedures to mitigate and manage effectively the ML/TF risks
          identified. These must be proportionate to the nature and size of
          the entity and must include:
          (a) internal policies covering: risk management, customer due
              diligence (CDD), reporting, record-keeping, internal control,
              compliance management (including, where appropriate, appointment
              of a compliance officer at management level), and employee
              screening;
          (b) where appropriate to the size and nature of the business, an
              independent audit function to test internal policies, controls,
              and procedures.
      (5) Senior management approval must be obtained for the policies,
          controls, and procedures put in place, and measures must be
          monitored and enhanced where appropriate.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER II — CUSTOMER DUE DILIGENCE (Articles 10–29)
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="II" title="Customer Due Diligence">

    <Article id="10" title="Prohibition of Anonymous Accounts"
             obligation_type="CDD — Prohibition">
      Credit institutions and financial institutions must not keep anonymous
      accounts or anonymous passbooks. Existing anonymous accounts must be
      subjected to CDD measures as soon as possible and before they are used
      in any way. Obliged entities must also take measures to prevent misuse
      of bearer shares and bearer share warrants.
    </Article>

    <Article id="11" title="Circumstances Requiring CDD"
             obligation_type="CDD — Trigger Events">
      Obliged entities must apply CDD measures in all of the following
      circumstances:
      (a) when establishing a business relationship;
      (b) when carrying out an occasional transaction of EUR 15,000 or more
          (single or linked operations), or a fund transfer exceeding EUR 1,000;
      (c) specifically for traders in goods: occasional cash transactions of EUR 10,000 or
          more (single or linked operations);
      (d) specifically for gambling service providers: transactions of EUR 2,000 or more
          (collection of winnings, wagering of a stake, or both);
      (e) whenever there is a suspicion of ML or TF, regardless of any
          threshold or exemption;
      (f) when there are doubts about the accuracy or adequacy of previously
          obtained customer identification data.
    </Article>

    <Article id="13" title="Standard CDD Measures — Content"
             obligation_type="CDD — Standard">
      Obliged entities must apply all of the following CDD measures (Standard Customer Due Diligence Measures):
      (a) CUSTOMER IDENTIFICATION: identify the customer and verify their
          identity using documents, data, or information from a reliable and
          independent source;
      (b) BENEFICIAL OWNER (UBO) IDENTIFICATION: identify the beneficial owner and
          take reasonable measures to verify their identity; for legal persons,
          trusts, and similar structures, understand the ownership and control
          structure;
      (c) PURPOSE OF RELATIONSHIP: assess and, where appropriate, obtain
          information on the purpose and intended nature of the business
          relationship;
      (d) ONGOING MONITORING: continuously monitor the business relationship,
          scrutinise transactions to ensure consistency with the customer's
          known business and risk profile (including source of funds where
          necessary), and keep all documents and data up to date.
      When identifying and verifying the customer and beneficial owner,
      obliged entities must also verify that any person purporting to act on
      behalf of the customer is duly authorised, and identify and verify that
      person's identity.
      CDD measures may be applied on a risk-sensitive basis to determine
      their extent, but all four elements above must be applied.
      Obliged entities must be able to demonstrate to competent authorities
      that the measures taken are appropriate given the identified ML/TF risks.
      For life insurance and investment-related insurance: in addition to
      standard CDD on the customer and beneficial owner, obliged entities must
      also identify the beneficiaries of the policy (by name, or by sufficient
      information to identify them at payout). Verification of beneficiary
      identity must occur at the time of payout. Where the policy is assigned
      to a third party, the beneficial owner of the assignee must be identified
      at the time of assignment.
      For trusts and similar arrangements with class beneficiaries: sufficient
      information must be obtained to identify beneficiaries at the time of
      payout or exercise of vested rights.
    </Article>

    <Article id="14" title="Timing of CDD — When Verification Must Occur"
             obligation_type="CDD — Timing">
      (1) Verification of customer and beneficial owner identity must normally
          be completed BEFORE establishing a business relationship or carrying
          out a transaction.
      (2) Exceptionally, verification may be completed DURING the establishment
          of a business relationship if interruption would disrupt normal
          business and ML/TF risk is low; it must then be completed as soon as
          practicable.
      (3) For account opening at credit or financial institutions: the account
          may be opened before verification is complete, provided that no
          transactions are carried out until full CDD under Article 13(1)(a)
          and (b) is obtained.
      (4) If an obliged entity cannot complete CDD requirements (Article
          13(1)(a), (b), or (c)), it must: not carry out the transaction, not
          establish the business relationship, terminate any existing
          relationship, and consider filing a suspicious transaction report
          (STR) with the FIU.
      (5) CDD must be applied not only to new customers but also to existing
          customers on a risk-sensitive basis, including when relevant
          circumstances change.
    </Article>

    <Article id="15" title="Simplified CDD — When Permitted"
             obligation_type="CDD — Simplified">
      Where lower ML/TF risk is identified (taking into account at least Annex II
      factors), obliged entities may apply simplified CDD measures. Before
      applying simplified CDD, the obliged entity must ascertain that the
      business relationship or transaction genuinely presents lower risk.
      Even when applying simplified CDD, obliged entities must carry out
      sufficient monitoring to detect unusual or suspicious transactions.
    </Article>

    <Article id="16" title="Simplified CDD — Risk Factors to Consider"
             obligation_type="CDD — Simplified">
      When assessing whether simplified CDD is appropriate, obliged entities
      must consider at least the Annex II factors, including:
      CUSTOMER factors: publicly listed companies with adequate ownership
      disclosure; public administrations; customers resident in lower-risk
      geographic areas.
      PRODUCT/SERVICE factors: low-premium life insurance; certain pension
      schemes; financial inclusion products; electronic money products with
      purse limits and ownership transparency.
      GEOGRAPHIC factors: EU Member States; third countries with effective
      AML/CFT systems; third countries with low corruption; third countries
      that effectively implement FATF Recommendations.
    </Article>

    <Article id="18" title="Enhanced CDD — When Required"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced">
      Obliged entities MUST apply enhanced CDD (EDD) measures in all of the
      following situations:
      — when dealing with customers or beneficial owners established in
        high-risk third countries identified by the Commission;
      — in the specific cases covered by Articles 18a–24 (cross-border
        correspondent banking, politically exposed persons, shell banks);
      — in any other higher-risk situation identified by the Member State or
        by the obliged entity itself (considering Annex III factors).
      In all EDD cases, obliged entities must examine, as far as reasonably
      possible, the background and purpose of complex, unusually large, or
      unusual-pattern transactions with no apparent economic or lawful purpose,
      and increase the degree and intensity of monitoring of those business
      relationships.
      Annex III higher-risk indicators include:
      CUSTOMER: unusual business circumstances; customers in high-risk
      geographic areas; personal asset-holding vehicles; nominee shareholders;
      cash-intensive businesses; unusual or excessively complex ownership
      structures.
      PRODUCT/SERVICE: private banking; products favouring anonymity;
      non-face-to-face relationships without adequate safeguards; payments
      from unknown third parties; new or developing technologies.
      GEOGRAPHIC: countries without effective AML/CFT systems; countries with
      high corruption; sanctioned countries; countries supporting terrorism.
    </Article>
	
	<Article id="18a" title="Enhanced CDD — Mandatory Measures for High-Risk Third Countries"
         obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — High-Risk Third Countries"
         introduced_by="Directive (EU) 2018/843 (AMLD5)"
         amends="Directive (EU) 2015/849 (AMLD4)">

  <!-- PARAGRAPH 1: Mandatory EDD measures — direct obligations on obliged entities -->
  <Paragraph id="1">
    For ALL business relationships or transactions involving high-risk third
    countries identified by the Commission under Article 9(2), obliged entities
    MUST apply ALL of the following enhanced CDD measures:
    (a) obtain additional information on the customer and on the beneficial
        owner(s);
    (b) obtain additional information on the intended nature of the business
        relationship;
    (c) obtain information on the source of funds and source of wealth of the
        customer and of the beneficial owner(s);
    (d) obtain information on the reasons for the intended or performed
        transactions;
    (e) obtain senior management approval for establishing or continuing the
        business relationship;
    (f) conduct enhanced ongoing monitoring by increasing the number and
        frequency of controls applied, and selecting patterns of transactions
        that need further examination.
    Member States may additionally require that, where applicable, the first
    payment be made through an account held in the customer's name at a credit
    institution subject to CDD standards at least as robust as those in this
    Directive.
  </Paragraph>

  <!-- PARAGRAPH 2: Additional mitigating measures — obligations on obliged entities
       where required by the Member State -->
  <Paragraph id="2"
             note="These measures apply where required by the Member State.
                   At least one must be imposed by each Member State.">
    In addition to the paragraph 1 measures, where required by their Member
    State, obliged entities must apply one or more of the following additional
    mitigating measures to persons and legal entities carrying out transactions
    involving high-risk third countries:
    (a) apply additional elements of enhanced due diligence beyond those in
        paragraph 1;
    (b) introduce enhanced or systematic reporting of financial transactions
        to the relevant authorities;
    (c) limit or restrict business relationships or transactions with natural
        persons or legal entities from the identified high-risk third country.
  </Paragraph>

  <!-- PARAGRAPH 3(e): The only paragraph 3 measure that creates a direct
       obligation on obliged entities; all other paragraph 3 measures are
       addressed to Member States and supervisory authorities. -->
  <Paragraph id="3e"
             note="Paragraphs 3(a)–(d) are measures applied by Member States
                   and supervisory authorities, not direct obligations on
                   obliged entities. Paragraph 3(e) is the exception.">
    Where required by their Member State, credit institutions and financial
    institutions must review and amend, or if necessary TERMINATE, correspondent
    relationships with respondent institutions located in the identified
    high-risk third country.
  </Paragraph>

  <!-- RELATIONSHIP TO ARTICLE 18 -->
  <Context>
    Article 18a creates a mandatory, exhaustive list of EDD measures specifically
    for high-risk third countries identified under Article 9(2). It operates
    alongside Article 18 (general enhanced CDD) but is more prescriptive:
    all paragraph 1 measures are compulsory, whereas Article 18 grants
    obliged entities greater discretion in selecting appropriate EDD measures.
    The paragraph 1 obligations on obliged entities are not contingent on
    Member State implementation choices.
  </Context>

	</Article>

    <Article id="19" title="Enhanced CDD — Cross-Border Correspondent Banking"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — Correspondent Banking">
      For cross-border correspondent relationships with third-country
      respondent institutions, credit institutions and financial institutions
      must, in addition to standard CDD:
      (a) gather sufficient information to fully understand the respondent's
          business and assess its reputation and quality of supervision from
          publicly available information;
      (b) assess the respondent institution's AML/CFT controls;
      (c) obtain senior management approval before establishing new
          correspondent relationships;
      (d) document the respective AML/CFT responsibilities of each institution;
      (e) for payable-through accounts: obtain satisfaction that the respondent
          has verified the identity of, and performs ongoing due diligence on,
          customers with direct access, and can provide relevant CDD data
          on request.
    </Article>
	
	xml<Article id="19a"
         title="Self-Hosted Address Risk Assessment and Mitigation — Crypto-Asset Service Providers"
         obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — Crypto-Assets — Self-Hosted Addresses"
         introduced_by="Directive (EU) 2024/1640 (AMLD6)"
         applies_to="Crypto-asset service providers (CASPs)">

  <Paragraph id="1">
    Crypto-asset service providers (CASPs) must identify and assess the ML/TF
    risk associated with transfers of crypto-assets directed to or originating
    from a SELF-HOSTED ADDRESS (i.e. a crypto-asset address not held by a
    regulated CASP or financial institution).

    To that end, CASPs must have in place internal policies, procedures, and
    controls specifically covering self-hosted address transfers.

    CASPs must apply mitigating measures commensurate with the risks identified.
    Those measures must include one or more of the following:
    (a) IDENTIFICATION: take risk-based measures to identify and verify the
        identity of the originator or beneficiary of the transfer to/from the
        self-hosted address, or the beneficial owner of such originator or
        beneficiary — including through reliance on third parties (Article 25);
    (b) ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: require additional information on the origin
        and destination of the transferred crypto-assets;
    (c) ENHANCED MONITORING: conduct enhanced ongoing monitoring of those
        transactions;
    (d) OTHER MEASURES: apply any other measure to mitigate and manage ML/TF
        risks as well as the risk of non-implementation or evasion of targeted
        financial sanctions (TFS) and proliferation-financing-related TFS.

    Note: The selection of measures must be proportionate to the risk level
    identified for each self-hosted address transfer. EBA guidelines (due by
    30 December 2024) will specify the criteria and means for identification
    and verification under this Article.
  </Paragraph>

</Article>


<Article id="19b"
         title="Enhanced CDD — Cross-Border Correspondent Relationships for Crypto-Asset Services"
         obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — Crypto-Assets — Correspondent Relationships"
         introduced_by="Directive (EU) 2024/1640 (AMLD6)"
         applies_to="Crypto-asset service providers (CASPs)"
         cross_reference="Mirrors Article 19 (correspondent banking) for crypto-assets;
                          Regulation (EU) 2023/1114 (MiCA), Article 3(1)(16) defines
                          crypto-asset services in scope — excluding custody and
                          administration of crypto-assets on behalf of clients (point (h))">

  <Paragraph id="1">
    For cross-border CORRESPONDENT RELATIONSHIPS involving the execution of
    crypto-asset services with a respondent entity NOT established in the EU
    and providing similar services (including crypto-asset transfers), CASPs
    must apply the following measures IN ADDITION to standard CDD under
    Article 13, when entering into a business relationship with such an entity:

    (a) LICENSING CHECK: determine whether the respondent entity is licensed
        or registered in its jurisdiction;
    (b) BUSINESS UNDERSTANDING: gather sufficient information to fully
        understand the nature of the respondent's business and assess, from
        publicly available information, its reputation and the quality of
        supervision it is subject to;
    (c) AML/CFT ASSESSMENT: assess the respondent entity's AML/CFT controls;
    (d) SENIOR MANAGEMENT APPROVAL: obtain senior management approval before
        establishing any new correspondent relationship;
    (e) RESPONSIBILITY DOCUMENTATION: document the respective AML/CFT
        responsibilities of each party to the correspondent relationship;
    (f) PAYABLE-THROUGH ACCOUNTS: where the arrangement involves
        payable-through crypto-asset accounts, obtain satisfaction that the
        respondent entity has verified the identity of, and performs ongoing
        due diligence on, customers with direct access to the correspondent
        entity's accounts, and that the respondent can provide relevant CDD
        data to the correspondent upon request.

    TERMINATION: Where a CASP decides to terminate a correspondent relationship
    for AML/CFT policy reasons, it must document and record the decision and
    the grounds for it.

    ONGOING UPDATES: CASPs must update their due diligence information for
    correspondent relationships on a regular basis and whenever new risks
    emerge in relation to the respondent entity.
  </Paragraph>

  <Paragraph id="2">
    CASPs must use the information gathered under paragraph 1 to determine,
    on a risk-sensitive basis, the appropriate additional mitigating measures
    to address the risks associated with the respondent entity.
    Note: EBA guidelines (due by 30 June 2024) will specify the assessment
    criteria and risk-mitigating measures under this Article, including minimum
    action where the respondent entity is unlicensed or unregistered.
  </Paragraph>

  <Context>
    Article 19b is the crypto-asset equivalent of Article 19 (cross-border
    correspondent banking). The key structural differences are:
    — CASPs must additionally verify whether the respondent is licensed or
      registered (paragraph 1(a)), which has no direct equivalent in Article 19;
    — CASPs must document termination decisions made on AML/CFT grounds
      (no equivalent in Article 19);
    — CASPs must keep due diligence information current on a regular basis
      and when new risks emerge (Article 19 implies but does not state this
      explicitly).
    The scope excludes custody and administration of crypto-assets on behalf
    of clients (MiCA Article 3(1)(16)(h)), meaning pure custody providers
    are not subject to this article's correspondent relationship regime.
  </Context>

</Article>

    <Article id="20" title="Enhanced CDD — Politically Exposed Persons (PEPs)"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — PEPs">
      For transactions or business relationships with politically exposed
      persons (PEPs), obliged entities must, in addition to standard CDD:
      (a) have in place risk-based procedures to determine whether the customer
          or beneficial owner is a PEP;
      (b) obtain senior management approval before establishing or continuing
          a business relationship with a PEP;
      (c) take adequate measures to establish the source of wealth and source
          of funds involved in the business relationship or transaction;
      (d) conduct enhanced, ongoing monitoring of the business relationship.
      PEP definition includes: heads of State/government, ministers, members
      of parliament, members of governing bodies of political parties, judges
      of supreme/constitutional courts, members of courts of auditors or
      central bank boards, ambassadors and senior military officers, directors
      of State-owned enterprises, and senior officials of international
      organisations. Middle-ranking and junior officials are excluded.
    </Article>

    <Article id="21" title="Enhanced CDD — PEPs as Insurance Beneficiaries"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — PEPs">
      For life and investment-related insurance, obliged entities must take
      reasonable measures to determine whether policy beneficiaries (or their
      beneficial owners) are PEPs. This check must be completed no later than
      at the time of payout or assignment. Where higher risk is identified,
      obliged entities must:
      (a) inform senior management before paying out policy proceeds;
      (b) conduct enhanced scrutiny of the entire business relationship with
          the policyholder.
    </Article>

    <Article id="22" title="Enhanced CDD — Former PEPs"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — PEPs">
      When a person ceases to hold a prominent public function, obliged
      entities must continue to apply appropriate and risk-sensitive EDD
      measures for at least 12 months, until the person is deemed to pose no
      further PEP-specific risk.
    </Article>

    <Article id="23" title="Enhanced CDD — PEP Family Members and Close Associates"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — PEPs">
      The EDD measures required for PEPs under Articles 20 and 21 must also
      be applied to family members and persons known to be close associates
      of PEPs. Family members include: spouse or equivalent, children and
      their spouses, and parents. Close associates include persons with joint
      beneficial ownership of legal entities/arrangements with the PEP, or
      persons who hold beneficial ownership of a legal entity/arrangement set
      up for the de facto benefit of the PEP.
    </Article>

    <Article id="24" title="Prohibition — Shell Bank Correspondent Relationships"
             obligation_type="CDD — Enhanced — Prohibition">
      Credit institutions and financial institutions must not enter into or
      continue correspondent relationships with shell banks (i.e., credit or
      financial institutions incorporated in a jurisdiction with no physical
      presence, meaningful mind and management, and no affiliation to a
      regulated financial group). They must also take appropriate measures to
      ensure they do not engage in or continue correspondent relationships
      with any institution that is known to allow its accounts to be used by
      a shell bank.
    </Article>

    <Article id="25" title="Reliance on Third Parties for CDD"
             obligation_type="CDD — Third-Party Reliance">
      Obliged entities may rely on third parties to carry out CDD requirements
      under Article 13(1)(a), (b), and (c) (customer identification, beneficial
      owner identification, and purpose of relationship). However, the
      ULTIMATE RESPONSIBILITY for meeting CDD requirements always remains with
      the obliged entity that relies on the third party.
    </Article>

    <Article id="26" title="Third Parties — Eligibility Conditions"
             obligation_type="CDD — Third-Party Reliance">
      An entity may only be relied upon as a third party for CDD if it:
      (a) applies CDD and record-keeping requirements consistent with this
          Directive; and
      (b) has its compliance with those requirements supervised in a manner
          consistent with this Directive.
      Obliged entities may NOT rely on third parties established in high-risk
      third countries identified by the Commission.
    </Article>

    <Article id="27" title="Third Parties — Information Requirements"
             obligation_type="CDD — Third-Party Reliance">
      When relying on a third party, the obliged entity must:
      (a) obtain from the third party all necessary information concerning
          the CDD requirements under Article 13(1)(a), (b), and (c);
      (b) take adequate steps to ensure that the third party will immediately
          provide, upon request, relevant copies of identification and
          verification data and other documentation on the identity of the
          customer or beneficial owner.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER III — BENEFICIAL OWNERSHIP INFORMATION
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="III" title="Beneficial Ownership Information">

    <Article id="30" title="Beneficial Ownership — Corporate Entities"
             obligation_type="Beneficial Ownership">
      Corporate and other legal entities must obtain and hold adequate,
      accurate, and current information on their beneficial ownership,
      including details of the beneficial interests held. They must provide
      this information to obliged entities when CDD measures are being
      applied.
      For obliged entities conducting CDD: do not rely exclusively on the
      central register to fulfil CDD requirements; use a risk-based approach.
      Beneficial owner definition for corporate entities: the natural person(s)
      who ultimately own or control the entity through direct or indirect
      ownership of more than 25% of shares/voting rights, or through other
      means of control. If no such person can be identified after exhausting
      all means, the senior managing official(s) may be treated as the
      beneficial owner(s), with records kept of the steps taken.
    </Article>

    <Article id="31" title="Beneficial Ownership — Trusts"
             obligation_type="Beneficial Ownership">
      Trustees must obtain and hold adequate, accurate, and up-to-date
      beneficial ownership information on the trust, covering: the settlor,
      trustee(s), protector (if any), beneficiaries or class of beneficiaries,
      and any other person exercising effective control over the trust.
      Trustees must disclose their status as trustee and provide the above
      information to obliged entities in a timely manner when forming a
      business relationship or carrying out an occasional transaction above the
      relevant thresholds. This obligation applies equally to other legal
      arrangements with structures or functions similar to trusts.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER IV — REPORTING OBLIGATIONS (Articles 32–39)
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="IV" title="Reporting Obligations">

    <Article id="33" title="Suspicious Transaction Reporting (STR)"
             obligation_type="Reporting">
      Obliged entities, their directors, and employees must:
      (a) PROACTIVE REPORTING: inform the FIU on their own initiative, by
          filing a suspicious transaction report (STR), where the entity
          knows, suspects, or has reasonable grounds to suspect that funds
          (regardless of amount) are proceeds of criminal activity or are
          related to terrorist financing; and promptly respond to requests by
          the FIU for additional information;
      (b) REACTIVE REPORTING: provide the FIU, directly or indirectly and
          upon request, with all necessary information in accordance with
          applicable law.
      All suspicious transactions, INCLUDING ATTEMPTED TRANSACTIONS, must
      be reported. The compliance officer (appointed under Article 8(4)(a))
      is responsible for transmitting the report to the FIU of the Member
      State where the entity is established.
    </Article>

    <Article id="35" title="Obligation to Refrain from Executing Suspicious Transactions"
             obligation_type="Reporting — Transaction Restraint">
      Obliged entities must refrain from executing transactions they know or
      suspect to be related to ML or TF until they have filed an STR under
      Article 33(1)(a) and complied with any further instructions from the
      FIU or competent authorities. If refraining is impossible or would
      frustrate efforts to pursue beneficiaries, the FIU must be informed
      immediately afterwards.
    </Article>

    <Article id="37" title="Safe Harbour for Good-Faith Reporting"
             obligation_type="Reporting — Protection">
      Disclosure of information in good faith by an obliged entity, or by
      its employees or directors, in accordance with Articles 33 and 34 does
      not constitute a breach of any contractual, legislative, regulatory, or
      administrative restriction on disclosure, and does not give rise to
      any liability, even if the underlying criminal activity was not precisely
      known or did not actually occur.
    </Article>

    <Article id="38" title="Whistleblower Protection"
             obligation_type="Reporting — Protection">
      Obliged entities must ensure that employees and representatives who
      report suspicions of ML or TF internally or to the FIU are protected
      from threats, hostile action, and adverse or discriminatory employment
      actions.
    </Article>

    <Article id="39" title="Tipping-Off Prohibition"
             obligation_type="Reporting — Confidentiality">
      Obliged entities, their directors, and employees must NOT disclose to
      the customer or any third party that an STR has been, is being, or will
      be filed, or that a ML/TF analysis is underway or may be carried out.
      Exceptions (disclosure is permitted):
      — to competent authorities or self-regulatory bodies, or for law
        enforcement purposes;
      — within a group (between credit/financial institutions and their
        group branches/subsidiaries in third countries), provided group-wide
        AML/CFT policies under Article 45 are fully complied with;
      — between obliged entities within the same legal person or structure
        sharing common ownership, management, or compliance control;
      — between obliged entities from the same professional category, dealing
        with the same customer and the same transaction, subject to equivalent
        AML/CFT and professional secrecy obligations.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER V — DATA PROTECTION AND RECORD-KEEPING
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="V" title="Data Protection, Record-Keeping, and Statistics">

    <Article id="40" title="Record-Keeping Obligations"
             obligation_type="Record-Keeping">
      Obliged entities must retain the following for FIVE YEARS after the
      end of the business relationship or the date of an occasional
      transaction:
      (a) CDD records: copies of documents and information used to comply
          with CDD requirements under Chapter II;
      (b) Transaction records: supporting evidence and transaction records
          (original documents or admissible copies) sufficient to identify
          each transaction.
      Upon expiry of the five-year period, personal data must be deleted
      unless national law provides otherwise. Retention may be extended for
      a further period not exceeding five additional years, if a thorough
      necessity and proportionality assessment justifies it for ML/TF
      prevention, detection, or investigation purposes.
    </Article>

    <Article id="41" title="Data Protection — Limits on Use of Personal Data"
             obligation_type="Data Protection">
      Obliged entities may process personal data under this Directive ONLY
      for the purpose of preventing ML and TF as referred to in Article 1.
      Further processing of that data for any other purpose, including
      commercial purposes, is strictly prohibited. Before establishing a
      business relationship or carrying out an occasional transaction, obliged
      entities must inform new clients of the legal obligations under this
      Directive to process their personal data for AML/CFT purposes.
    </Article>

    <Article id="42" title="Systems for Responding to FIU Enquiries"
             obligation_type="Record-Keeping — Systems">
      Obliged entities must have in place systems that enable them to respond
      fully and promptly, through secure and confidential channels, to enquiries
      from the FIU or other competent authorities as to whether they are
      maintaining, or have maintained within the previous five years, a
      business relationship with a specified person, and on the nature of
      that relationship.
    </Article>

    <Article id="43" title="Data Processing as Public Interest"
             obligation_type="Data Protection">
      The processing of personal data for ML/TF prevention under this
      Directive is to be treated as a matter of public interest. Obliged
      entities may restrict a data subject's right of access to personal data
      to the extent necessary to enable the entity or competent authority to
      fulfil its AML/CFT functions or to avoid obstructing official
      investigations or analyses.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       CHAPTER VI — POLICIES, PROCEDURES, AND SUPERVISION
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Chapter id="VI" title="Internal Policies, Training, and Group Requirements">

    <Article id="45" title="Group-Wide AML/CFT Policies and Procedures"
             obligation_type="Internal Controls — Group">
      Obliged entities that are part of a group must implement group-wide
      policies and procedures that include:
      — data protection policies;
      — procedures for sharing information within the group for AML/CFT
        purposes;
      — the requirement that these policies be effectively implemented at
        all branches and majority-owned subsidiaries in Member States and
        third countries.
      Where a branch or subsidiary is in a third country with less strict
      AML/CFT requirements, the group must apply the home Member State's
      higher standards to the extent permitted by local law.
      Where local law does not permit full implementation, the obliged entity
      must apply additional measures to manage the residual risk and inform
      the home competent authority. The sharing of ML/TF suspicion information
      within the group is permitted (and may be required), unless the FIU
      instructs otherwise.
    </Article>

    <Article id="46" title="Employee Training and Awareness"
             obligation_type="Internal Controls — Training">
      Obliged entities must take measures proportionate to their risks, nature,
      and size to ensure that:
      (a) all relevant employees are aware of applicable AML/CFT provisions,
          including data protection requirements;
      (b) employees participate in ongoing, specialised training programmes to
          help them recognise ML/TF operations and know how to proceed when
          such operations are identified;
      (c) employees have access to up-to-date information on current ML/TF
          methods and indicators for recognising suspicious transactions;
      (d) where practicable, timely feedback on the effectiveness and follow-up
          of their ML/TF reports is provided;
      (e) where applicable, the member of the management board responsible for
          AML/CFT compliance implementation is identified.
    </Article>

  </Chapter>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       ANNEXES — RISK FACTOR REFERENCE LISTS
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <Annexes>

    <Annex id="I" title="CDD Risk Variables (Article 13(3))"
           usage="Obliged entities must consider these variables when
                  determining the extent of CDD measures to apply.">
      Non-exhaustive list:
      (i)   the purpose of an account or business relationship;
      (ii)  the level of assets to be deposited or the size of transactions;
      (iii) the regularity or duration of the business relationship.
    </Annex>

    <Annex id="II" title="Potentially Lower-Risk Factors (Articles 15–16)"
           usage="Obliged entities may apply simplified CDD where these
                  factors indicate genuinely lower ML/TF risk.">
      CUSTOMER factors: publicly listed companies with adequate ownership
      disclosure; public administrations; customers in lower-risk geographic
      areas.
      PRODUCT/SERVICE factors: low-premium life insurance; certain
      non-assignable pension schemes; financial inclusion products; electronic
      money with purse limits and ownership transparency.
      GEOGRAPHIC factors: EU Member States; third countries with effective
      AML/CFT systems; third countries with low corruption; third countries
      that effectively implement the revised FATF Recommendations.
    </Annex>

    <Annex id="III" title="Potentially Higher-Risk Factors (Article 18(3))"
           usage="Obliged entities must apply enhanced CDD where these
                  factors indicate higher ML/TF risk.">
      CUSTOMER factors: unusual business circumstances; customers in
      high-risk geographic areas; personal asset-holding vehicles; companies
      with nominee shareholders or bearer shares; cash-intensive businesses;
      unusual or excessively complex ownership structures.
      PRODUCT/SERVICE factors: private banking; products favouring anonymity;
      non-face-to-face relationships without adequate safeguards; payments
      from unknown or unassociated third parties; new products, delivery
      mechanisms, or technologies.
      GEOGRAPHIC factors: countries without effective AML/CFT systems; high
      corruption countries; countries under UN/EU sanctions or embargoes;
      countries providing funding or support for terrorist activities.
    </Annex>

  </Annexes>

  <!-- ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════
       QUICK-REFERENCE: OBLIGATION TAXONOMY BY TYPE
       ═══════════════════════════════════════════════════════ -->

  <ObligationIndex>
    <Category name="Risk Assessment and Internal Controls">
      <Ref article="8"  summary="Conduct, document, and update ML/TF risk assessments; maintain proportionate policies, controls, and procedures; obtain senior management approval"/>
      <Ref article="45" summary="Implement group-wide AML/CFT policies at all branches and subsidiaries"/>
      <Ref article="46" summary="Train employees; identify the management-board AML/CFT responsible person"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Customer Due Diligence — Standard">
      <Ref article="10" summary="No anonymous accounts; prevent bearer share misuse"/>
      <Ref article="11" summary="Apply CDD on business relationship establishment, transactions above thresholds, and upon suspicion"/>
      <Ref article="13" summary="Core CDD: identify customer, identify beneficial owner, assess relationship purpose, conduct ongoing monitoring"/>
      <Ref article="14" summary="Timing of CDD: verify before relationship/transaction; inability to complete CDD → do not proceed, consider STR"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Customer Due Diligence — Simplified">
      <Ref article="15" summary="Simplified CDD permitted where lower risk is demonstrated; ongoing monitoring still required"/>
      <Ref article="16" summary="Consider Annex II factors when assessing eligibility for simplified CDD"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Customer Due Diligence — Enhanced">
      <Ref article="18" summary="Enhanced CDD mandatory for high-risk third countries and other higher-risk situations (Annex III)"/>
      <Ref article="18a" summary="For ALL business relationships/transactions involving Commission-listed
                                  high-risk third countries: mandatory application of all six paragraph 1
                                  EDD measures (additional customer/UBO information, relationship purpose,
                                  source of funds/wealth, transaction reasons, senior management approval,
                                  enhanced monitoring); plus one or more additional Member-State-required
                                  mitigating measures (paragraph 2); credit and financial institutions
                                  may additionally be required to review, amend, or terminate
                                  correspondent relationships with respondents in those countries
                                  (paragraph 3(e))"/>
	  <Ref article="19" summary="Additional EDD for cross-border correspondent banking with third-country respondents"/>
      <Ref article="20" summary="Additional EDD for PEPs: risk procedures, senior management approval, source of wealth/funds, enhanced monitoring"/>
      <Ref article="21" summary="Check insurance beneficiaries for PEP status; senior management notification and enhanced scrutiny if higher risk"/>
      <Ref article="22" summary="Maintain EDD for former PEPs for at least 12 months after leaving public function"/>
      <Ref article="23" summary="Apply PEP EDD measures to PEP family members and close associates"/>
      <Ref article="24" summary="Prohibition: no correspondent relationships with shell banks"/>
    </Category>
	  <Category name="Crypto-Asset Service Providers (CASPs)">
      <Ref article="19a" summary="Identify and assess ML/TF risk of transfers to/from self-hosted
                                  addresses; maintain internal policies and controls; apply
                                  commensurate mitigating measures (risk-based identification of
                                  originator/beneficiary, additional information on origin/destination,
                                  enhanced monitoring, or other TFS/proliferation-financing measures)"/>
      <Ref article="19b" summary="For cross-border correspondent relationships with non-EU crypto-asset
                                  service providers: verify licensing status; assess reputation,
                                  supervision quality, and AML/CFT controls; obtain senior management
                                  approval; document responsibilities; apply payable-through account
                                  safeguards; document AML/CFT-driven termination decisions; update
                                  due diligence regularly and when new risks emerge; apply
                                  risk-sensitive mitigating measures based on the assessment"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Third-Party CDD Reliance">
      <Ref article="25" summary="May rely on eligible third parties for CDD; ultimate responsibility remains with the obliged entity"/>
      <Ref article="26" summary="Third parties must meet AML/CFT standards; cannot rely on third parties in high-risk third countries"/>
      <Ref article="27" summary="Must obtain all necessary CDD information from the third party; must be able to obtain documents immediately on request"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Beneficial Ownership">
      <Ref article="30" summary="Legal entities must hold accurate beneficial ownership information and provide it to obliged entities during CDD; do not rely solely on central register"/>
      <Ref article="31" summary="Trustees must hold and disclose beneficial ownership information; applies also to trust-like arrangements"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Reporting">
      <Ref article="33" summary="File STRs proactively with the FIU on suspicion of ML/TF; respond to FIU information requests; report all suspicious and attempted transactions"/>
      <Ref article="35" summary="Refrain from executing suspicious transactions until STR is filed and FIU instructions are received"/>
      <Ref article="37" summary="Good-faith reporting is legally protected"/>
      <Ref article="38" summary="Protect whistleblowers from retaliation"/>
      <Ref article="39" summary="Do not tip off the customer or third parties that an STR has been filed or that a ML/TF investigation is underway"/>
    </Category>
    <Category name="Record-Keeping and Data Protection">
      <Ref article="40" summary="Retain CDD records and transaction records for 5 years; delete personal data on expiry unless extended retention is justified"/>
      <Ref article="41" summary="Process personal data only for AML/CFT purposes; no commercial reuse; inform new clients of data processing obligations"/>
      <Ref article="42" summary="Maintain systems to respond promptly and securely to FIU enquiries about business relationships within the past 5 years"/>
      <Ref article="43" summary="AML/CFT data processing is a public-interest matter; access rights of data subjects may be restricted as necessary"/>
    </Category>
  </ObligationIndex>

</AMLD4_ObligedEntity_Obligations>
